Merrill Moore Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Literary File, circa 1923-1958 (Box E1-E122)
  - 1930
    - Sonnets of American Life, (1 folder); (1 vol.) (Box E19)
    - The Streams of Sleep, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
  - 1931, O Glimmering World, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E20)
  - 1932
    - Twitter of Swallows, (1 vol.); (1 folder) (Box E21)
  - 1933
    - Capricious Ship, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Cold Language, (1 vol.); (4 folders) (Box E22)
    - Document, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Hypnogogische Bilder, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E23)
    - In Many Veins, (1 vol.); (6 folders) (Box E24)
    - A Lot of Sonnets, (1 vol.); (1 folder) (Box E25)
    - Loud Century, (1 vol. and 3 folders)
    - Record of Flight, (1 vol. and 6 folders) (Box E26)
    - Regarding Baldur, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E27)
    - Salty Derision, (1 vol.); (6 folders) (Box E28)
    - Sonnets Written
    - Stimulants, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Thirty Sonnets, (1 vol. and 2 folders) (Box E29)
    - Waves and Cities, (1 vol.); (6 folders) (Box E30)
    - Witness of Combat, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Eyes Sightless, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E31)
  - 1934
    - Not in Lone Splendor, (1 vol.); (1 folder) (Box E32)
    - Paroles d'un croyant, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Sonnets Written, (3 folders)
    - The Swimmer, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E33)
  - 1935
    - The Road Is Lonely
    - Six Sides to a Man (Box E34)
      - Author's manuscript, typescript carbon, page proofs, galley proofs, and reviews, (5 vols.)
      - Reviews, (2 vols.) (Box E35)
      - Sonnets, (6 folders)
    - Sonnets Written, (5 folders) (Box E36)
  - 1936
    - Of Prophesy, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
    - Sonnets Written, (8 folders) (Box E37)
  - 1937, Sonnets Written, (8 folders) (Box E38)
  - 1938 (Box E39)
    - M: One Thousand Autobiographical Sonnets
      - Bound letters of acknowledgment (Box E40)
    - Sonnets Written, (5 folders); (3 folders) (Box E41)
  - 1938-1939, Sonnets Written, (8 folders)
  - 1939, Sonnets Written, (2 folders) (Box E42)
  - 1939-1940, Sonnets Written, (2 folders)
  - 1940, Sonnets Written
  - 1941, Sonnets Written
  - 1942, Sonnets Written, (2 folders)
  - 1943, Sonnets Written, (4 folders)
  - 1944, Sonnets Written, (4 folders) (Box E43)
  - 1945, Sonnets Written, (7 folders); (12 folders); (11 folders); (6 folders) (Box E44, Box E45, Box E46)
  - 1946, Sonnets Written, (6 folders); (10 folders); (9 folders) (Box E47, Box E48)
  - 1947, Sonnets Written, (2 folders); (9 folders) (Box E49)
  - 1948, Sonnets Written, (1 folder); (9 folders) (Box E50)
  - 1949, Sonnets Written, (1 folder); (10 folders); (3 folders) (Box E51, Box E52)
  - 1950, Sonnets Written, (7 folders); (10 folders) (Box E53, Box E54)
  - 1951, Sonnets Written, (3 folders); (10 folders); (7 folders) (Box E55, Box E56, Box E57, Box E58, Box E59, Box E60, Box E61, Box E62)
  - 1952, Sonnets Written, (3 folders); (10 folders); (1 folder) (Box E63, Box E64, Box E65, Box E66, Box E67, Box E68, Box E69, Box E70)
  - 1953, Sonnets Written, (9 folders); (10 folders); (7 folders) (Box E71, Box E72)
  - 1954
    - Sonnets Written, (3 folders); (10 folders); (6 folders) (Box E73, Box E74)
  - 1955
    - A Psychiatrist's Book of Hours, (1 vol.); (6 folders) (Box E75)
    - Sonnets Written
    - Verse-Diary of a Psychiatrist
  - 1956
    - Sonnets Written, (3 folders); (7 folders) (Box E76)
  - 1957, Sonnets Written
  - 1958, Poems of American Life, printer's proofs
  - Undated, Sonnets Written, (10 folders) (Box E77, Box E78, Box E79, Box E80, Box E81, Box E82, Box E83)
  - Partial card index of sonnets written, 1922-1951, including numerous complete sonnets (Box E84)
  - Bound index to Unrecorded Things, The Urgency of Twilight, Dance of Death, More Sonnets in the American Tradition, A Sonnet Gallery of American Portraits, The Streams of Sleep, Sonnets of American Life, Quickened to Sympathy, O Glimmering World, and Twitter of Swallows (Box E85)
  - Bound index to Thirty Sonnets, Loud Century, Waves and Cities, Salty Derision, Record of Flight, In Many Veins, Cold Language, Capricious Ship, Hypnogogische Bilder
  - Abstract Surrealist
  - Americanische Sonnetten. A notebook of sonnets from The Noise That Time Makes translated into German
  - An Entire Book of One Hundred Sonnets
  - Boston Common People, (3 folders) (Box E86)
  - Childe Merrill, (3 vols.)
  - China (Box E87)
  - Conclusions, (1 vol. and 1 folder)
  - Dawn Honey, (3 folders); (1 vol.) (Box E88)
  - Day and Night
  - Ego, (1 vol. and 1 folder); (3 vols.) (Box E89)
  - Experimental Sonnets, (1 folder)
  - Fragments, (2 vols. and 1 folder); (1 vol. and 6 folders) (Box E90, Box E91)
  - The Fugitive and Fugitive group (Box E92)
    - Prose from The Fugitive
    - Miscellany about The Fugitive and Fugitive group
    - Clippings about The Fugitive and Fugitive group, (2 vols.)
    - M.A. thesis, A History of the Fugitives and The Fugitive, 1938
  - German translations of miscellaneous sonnets (Box E93)
  - Juvenile
  - Juvenilia of a Young Poet, (1 vol. and 3 folders)
  - Leaves From a Psychiatrist's Notebook, (6 folders) (Box E94)
  - Literary theme, (2 folders)
  - Love theme
  - Medical theme
  - Moore, Merrill (Box E1-E99)
    - Miscellaneous publications in which his writings appear
    - Papers, lectures, articles, reviews, and miscellaneous published and unpublished prose writings of Merrill Moore, including notes and fragments (arranged alphabetically by title and subject) (Box E100-E103)
    - Published works (Box E104-E107)
    - Material relating to methods and techniques used by Moore in writing sonnets (Box E108-E109)
  - More Clinical Sonnets, (5 folders) (Box E110)
  - Non-Sonnet Forms, (1 vol.); (5 folders) (Box E111)
  - Pacific Warrior, (5 folders); (10 folders) (Box E112)
  - Pastoral (Box E113)
  - People, (6 folders)
  - Philosophic, (3 folders)
  - Philosophic, (10 folders) (Box E114)
  - Phoenix, (1 vol. and 1 folder) (Box E115)
  - Poems, (1 vol. and 4 folders)
  - Poems from The Fugitive and Fugitives, an Anthology of Verse, (2 vols.) (Box E116)
  - Poems, miscellaneous, (2 folders); (7 folders) (Box E117)
  - Poems read at Fugitive meetings by members of the group
  - Poetry as Usual, (10 folders); (2 folders) (Box E118, Box E119)
  - Psychiatric
  - Psychological
  - Sex-Love-Marriage, (5 folders)
  - Some Notes on Early Poems
  - Some Poems, (2 vols.) (Box E120)
  - Some War Poems
  - Sonnetten aus dem amerikanischen Leben
  - Sonnets Are Gizmos, (3 folders)
  - Sonnets for a General Psychiatrist, notebook (Box E121)
  - Sonnets from The Fugitive, (4 folders)
  - Time theme, (3 folders)
  - Time Will Not Stay
  - The Times and Troubles of the Form Divine (Box E122)
  - Tourist poems, (2 folders)
  - The Tradition That We Uphold, (1 vol. and 4 folders)
  - War theme
  - The Year
- Scrapbooks (Oversize), 1911-1948 (Box OV F1-OV F76)
  Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, usually focusing on a particular topic, supplemented by occasional miscellaneous material.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1911-1928, programs (Box OV F1)
  - circa 1919-1921, clippings, photographs, and occasional correspondence and notes (Box OV F2)
  - circa 1921-1933, holograph, typed, and clipped poems, mainly by others, including one letter (Box OV F3)
  - 1923; 1928, mementos of trips to Europe, including photographs, cards, clippings, and occasional correspondence (Box OV F4)
  - circa 1930-1931, clippings and occasional notes on neurology (Box OV F5)
  - 1932-1937, clippings and memoranda on suicide (Box OV F6)
  - circa 1934-1941, clippings on music (Box OV F7)
  - circa 1934-1942, clippings on books and poetry (Box OV F8)
  - 1936-1937, clippings on suicide (Box OV F9)
  - 1937, clippings on suicide (Box OV F10)
  - 1938, clippings from New York Times on miscellaneous topics (Box OV F11)
  - circa 1938-1939, clippings on miscellaneous topics (Box OV F12)
  - circa 1940, clippings on gardening (Box OV F13)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on alcohol (Box OV F14)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on animals and science (Box OV F15)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on drug addiction (Box OV F16)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on miscellaneous topics (Box OV F17-OV F18)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on occupations and hobbies (Box OV F19)
  - circa 1940-1941, clippings on recipes (Box OV F20)
  - circa 1940-1942, clippings on medicine (Box OV F21)
  - circa 1940-1942, clippings on psychology (Box OV F22)
  - circa 1940-1944, clippings on occupations and (Box OV F23)
  - circa 1940-1944, clippings on people and achievement (Box OV F24)
  - circa 1941, clippings on people (Box OV F25)
  - circa 1941, clippings on recipes (Box OV F26)
  - circa 1941, clippings on women, marriage, and miscellaneous (Box OV F27)
  - circa 1941-1942, clippings, cards, orders, memoranda, schedules, announcements, and notes on Fitzsimons General Hospital, Aurora, Colo. (Box OV F28)
  - circa 1942, clippings on miscellaneous topics (Box OV F29)
  - circa 1942-1946, clippings on Moore (Box OV F30)
  - circa 1944, clippings from military publications and a few military manuals (Box OV F31-OV F32)
  - Clippings from English-language Chinese newspapers and American publications in China (Box OV F33)
    - 1945-1946, Jan.
    - 1946 (Box OV F34)
      - Feb., (1 vol.) (Box OV F35)
      - Feb.-Mar. (Box OV F36)
      - Mar., (1 vol.) (Box OV F37, Box OV F38)
      - Mar.-Apr. (Box OV F39)
      - Apr., (1 vol.) (Box OV F40, Box OV F41)
      - May, (1 vol.) (Box OV F42, Box OV F43, Box OV F44, Box OV F45, Box OV F46, Box OV F47, Box OV F48)
      - May-June (Box OV F49)
      - June, (1 vol.) (Box OV F50, Box OV F51, Box OV F52)
      - June-July, (1 vol.) (Box OV F53, Box OV F54)
      - July-Aug. (Box OV F55)
      - Aug., (1 vol.) (Box OV F56, Box OV F57, Box OV F58, Box OV F59, Box OV F60)
      - Aug.-Sept. (Box OV F61)
      - Sept., (1 vol.) (Box OV F62, Box OV F63)
      - Sept.-Oct. (Box OV F64)
      - Oct.-Nov., (1 vol.) (Box OV F65, Box OV F66)
      - Nov.-Dec. (Box OV F67)
    - 1946, Dec.-1947, Jan (Box OV F68)
  - Clippings from Boston, Mass., area newspapers on miscellaneous topics (Box OV F69-OV F70)
  - Clippings and cards on children (Box OV F71)
  - Clippings on animals and science (Box OV F72)
  - Clippings on household goods and arts (Box OV F73)
  - Clippings on household goods and books (Box OV F74-OV F75)
  - Clippings on recreational activities and gifts (Box OV F76)
- Clippings, circa 1920-1957 (Box G1-G20)
  Chiefly unbound newspaper clippings.
  Arranged chronologically with some overlapping of material.
  - circa 1920-1957, miscellaneous clippings relating mainly to Moore (Box G1-G7)
  - 1923-1935, bound clippings relating mainly to Moore's literary activities, (6 vols.) (Box G8)
  - Clippings from New Zealand newspapers (Box G9)
    - 1942, Nov.-Dec.
    - 1942, Dec.-1943, Jan. (Box G10)
    - 1943 (Box G11)
      - Feb.-Mar.
      - Mar.-Apr. (Box G12)
      - Apr.-May (Box G13)
      - June-Aug. (Box G14)
      - Aug.-Sept. (Box G15)
      - Oct. (Box G16)
      - Oct.-Nov. (Box G17)
      - Nov.-Dec. (Box G18)
    - circa 1943-1944 (Box G19)
  - Clippings relating generally to the Far East, 1948-1949 (Box G20)
- Miscellany, 1920-1957 (Box H1-H9)
  Research notes, miscellaneous notes, a fragment of an appointment book, an unidentified bibliography of reprints, a deposition, invitations, and a speech.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Appointment book, 1935, Aug. 22-Dec. 31 (Box H1)
  - Bibliography of reprints
  - Deposition, Emerson Drug Co.
  - Graduation address, 1943, May 7
  - Invitation, awards, etc.
  - Notes
    - Alcoholism
    - Children
    - Psychiatry
    - South Pacific
  - Printed matter
    - Alcohol
    - Literary
    - Literary (Box H2)
    - Medical
    - Military
    - Psychology
    - Textbooks
  - Research material
  - Research material (Box H3-H4)
  - General miscellany (Box H5-H8)
- Addition, 1930-1979 (Box J1-J8)
  Family correspondence, general correspondence, miscellany, and research material.
  The family correspondence is arranged by name of family member and the general correspondence is organized chronologically.
  - Family correspondence (Box J1)
    - Cole, Whitefoord R., Jr.
      - Cole, Mary Bass, undated
    - Moore, Adam G. N.
      - Barnes, Bess Daniel, 1952-1957
      - Cole, Helen Moore, 1949-1979
      - Cole, Whitefoord R., Jr., 1949-1979
      - Cole, Whitefoord R. III, 1956-1979
      - Merrill, Pearl D., 1951-1953
      - Moore, Ann Leslie, 1946-1960
      - Moore, Hester, 1949-1959
      - Moore, John T., 1954-1960
      - Moore, Leslie, 1945, 1951-1960
      - Moore, Mary Daniel (Mrs. John Trotwood Moore), 1941, 1950-1957
      - Moore, Merrill
        - 1942-1946, (5 folders)
        - 1947-1957, (7 folders) (Box J2)
      - Whitney, Mary Daniel Moore, 1949-1979
      - Whitney, Shirley (Mrs. John T. Moore, Jr.), 1960
    - Moore, Ann Leslie
      - Cole, Helen Moore, 1977; Cole, Whitefoord R., Jr., 1954, 1960
      - Moore, Adam G. N., 1960, undated; Moore, Hester, 1957
      - Moore, Leslie, 1945-1960
    - Moore, Hester
      - Moore, Adam G. H., 1959
    - Moore, Merrill and Ann Leslie
      - Cole, Whitefoord R., Jr., 1949-1954
      - Moore, Adam G. N., 1944-1957, (7 folders)
      - Moore, John T., 1956-1957
      - Moore, Mary Daniel, 1941; 1949
      - Whitney, Mary Daniel Moore, 1945
    - Moore, Mary Daniel (Mrs. John Trotwood Moore)
      - Moore, Hester; Moore, John, 1957; Moore, Leslie, 1957
    - Nichol, Adam
      - Moore, Hester, 1949
    - Nichol, Ann Leslie
      - Moore, Merrill, 1930
    - Whitney, John
      - Cole, Helen Moore, 1960
  - General correspondence, 1942-1979, undated, (7 folders) (Box J3)
  - Miscellany, papers and correspondence relating to the Phillips Academy, 1949-1950, (2 folders)
  - Research material, 1954-1979 See also Container B47, Morgan, Christiana D., and Henry Murray; and Container B47, Murray, Henry A., Jr., and Robert N. Wilson (Box J4-J8)